Guide to the W. Stephen Coleman Papers, 1981-2011 CTC.2011.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
W. Stephen Coleman Papers
1981-2011
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Coleman, W. Stephen
CTC.2011.01
18 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
This collection contains the promptbooks, scripts, and production notes of W. Stephen Coleman (1943-). Dr. Coleman served as a faculty director and professor in the Theatre Arts department at the University of Pittsburgh (1981-2011) and a resident director for the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival (1983-1992). This collection details both acting and directing projects while in residence in the Pittsburgh area.
Biography
W. Stephen Coleman, Associate Professor and Director of Undergraduate Studies at the University of Pittsburgh, received his Bachelor's and Master's degrees from the University of Oklahoma in the mid 1960's, and his Doctorate from the University of Utah in 1973. As a specialist in Shakespeare in performance and the performance areas of actor-training and directing, he joined the undergraduate and graduate faculty of the University of Pittsburgh in 1981 as head of the then newly created MFA Actor Training Program, a post he held until 1990. Between 1992 and 1999, he served as Chair of the Department of Theatre Arts. He taught at several other universities and colleges, including the University of Texas at Austin, the London International Film School, Carnegie Mellon University, the University of Utah, the University of Oklahoma, and the Oklahoma College of Liberal Arts. He was awarded tenure at Pitt in 1986.
Dr. Coleman continued to work professionally, dividing his time between acting (under the name "Alex Coleman") and directing. In 2006 he played the role of First Messenger in Oedipus the King directed by Ted Pappas for the Pittsburgh Public Theatre. In 2005 he played the role of General Edward Braddock in the PBS/WQED four-part series, The War That Made America. At the University of Pittsburgh Repertory Theatre he played Uncle Peck in Paula Vogel's How I Learned to Drive (2002) and Estragon in Beckett's Waiting For Godot (2001), which he also directed. He also held three roles in the 2001 Season of the Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre: Sly Scully in the American premiere of Marina Carr's Portia Coughlin, Orgon in Tartuffe, and Dr. Hickey in the American premiere of Thomas Kilroy's adaptation of Chekhov's The Seagull. As "faculty guest artist" for the University of Pittsburgh Repertory Theatre he has also performed in such productions as Marat/Sade, playing de Sade, as Frank in Educating Rita, and John Halder in GOOD.
Other Pittsburgh professional stage performances include Reb Nachman and the Judge in the Pittsburgh Public Theatre's The Dybbuk, and both director of and lead in the sold-out run of Anthony Shaffer's Sleuth at Hartwood Acres. While it was a mainstay of Pitt's theatrical scene, Dr. Coleman appeared in over a dozen major roles with the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. He has performed with the New York Shakespeare Festival, the National Shakespeare Company, the Montana Repertory Theatre, and several other regional theatres. He is a long-time member of Actors' Equity Association, the Screen Actors Guild, and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists.
In addition to over 200 roles on the stage, he has played featured roles in a number of films and TV movies including the feature films Achilles' Love, House Guest, Silence of The Lambs (as the unfortunate Sergeant Pembry), The Dark Half, and Street Law, and the made-for-television movies, Alone in The Neon Jungle, What She Doesn't Know, The Ten-Million Dollar Getaway, and many others. He has performed in hundreds of radio and television commercials, and has appeared in numerous industrial films.
Coleman was a prolific director. At the Pitt Repertory Theatre from 2000 to 2006 he staged Old Times, Twelfth Night, the gala production of Much Ado About Nothing for the dedication of the newly renovated Charity Randall Theatre on the Pitt Campus, Arms and The Man, Waiting For Godot (mentioned above), and Little Shop of Horrors. He directed the world premiere of Daniel Frezza's adaptation of Oscar Wilde's The Picture of Dorian Gray (2000) for the Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre. He served as a faculty director for Pitt Repertory Theatre (1982- ) and in 1996 staged a highly acclaimed Hamlet and Rosencrantz and Guildenstern are Dead in repertory.
Between 1983 and 1992 he served as one of two Resident Directors for the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival (TRSF). His directorial efforts for both TRSF and the University were consistently cited as among the "Top Ten" in Pittsburgh from 1983-2006. He directed for numerous professional theatres in the Pittsburgh region, including the theatre at Hartwood Acres, (Sleuth and One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest). He also staged the world premiere of Pennsylvania State Poet Samuel Hazo's Until I'm Not Here Anymore and directed the video adaptation of this work that aired on Public Television.
In addition to his theatrical activities, Dr. Coleman staged readings for the Center for Creative Non-Fiction at the University of Pittsburgh. He was a regular presenter of lectures and workshops on performance subjects related to acting, directing, Shakespearean production, and the development of theatre skills that can be used in the courtroom. During his tenure at the University of Texas at Austin, he was the Founder and Artistic Director of the Gallimaufry Players, producing and directing four summers' worth of free Shakespeare-In-The-Park.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the promptbooks and production materials maintained by W. Stephen Coleman during his residence at the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival and the University of Pittsburgh Theatre Arts Department. It also includes materials for professional and non-professional acting engagements and directing projects undertaken by Coleman during his Pittsburgh years. Production materials contain rehearsal and director notes, press materials, set and costume designs, and miscellaneous administrative materials. Promptbooks, Production Materials, and Recordings in various formats (audio and VHS video) comprise the bulk of the collection. The collection is arranged in three series: Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival, University of Pittsburgh Repertory Theatre, and Acting and Directing.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of W. Stephen Coleman in April, 2011. Additional materials were added in October 2015.
Related Material
Kathleen George Papers, 1962-2014, CTC.2012.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre Records, 1997-2015, CTC.2009.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival Records, 1980-1995, CTC.1995.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
University of Pittsburgh Theatre Arts Department Records, 1960-1986, CTC.1974.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Arrangement
The papers are organized into three series.
Series I. Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival, 1983-1999
Series II. Pitt Repertory Theatre, 1981-2009
Series III. Acting and Directing, 1981-2011
Previous Citation
W. Stephen Coleman Papers, 1981-2011, CTC.2011.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 -- Stage history -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Pittsburgh Public Theater; Pittsburgh Irish and Classical Theatre; Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival (Pittsburgh, Pa.); University of Pittsburgh. Department of Theatre Arts; Coleman, W. Stephen
- Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival, 1981-1999; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains administrative files, promptbooks, and production materials from Pittsburgh's Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival for which W. Stephen Coleman was a resident director from 1983-1992. Coleman served as Interim Producing Director during the 1985 festival. This year is more thoroughly represented in the administrative files. In addition to numerous Shakespearean productions, this series also features Maids and Blades, an original staging featuring Shakespeare's romance and action scenes, and A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum. Also included is the musical version of Two Gentlemen of Verona, which was developed by Coleman and Christine Frezza and became a landmark production for the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival.
  Production materials can include audition forms, director's notes, rehearsal notes, production notes, set and costume designs, administrative information, press materials, photographs, programs, and brochures. Each production has been arranged into its own subseries and are in chronological order.
  - Administrative Files, 1.
    - 1982 Festival administration files, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1982 Festival administration files - Company manual (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1983 Festival administration files (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1984 Festival administration files (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1984 Festival administration files - Company manual (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1985 Festival administration files, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Carol Brown and Allegheny County Bureau of Cultural Programs correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Casting, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Citiparks, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Company manual (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - High school matinees (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Housing, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Production stage manager (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Romeo and Juliet (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Staff meetings, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Technical staff (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Touring (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Twelfth Night (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1985 Festival administration files - Yossi Yzraely (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1986 Festival administration files (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1986 Festival administration files - Company manual (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1988 Festival administration files - Company manual (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1989 Festival administration files, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1989 Festival administration files - Company manual (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1989 Festival administration files - Hamlet (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1991 Festival administration files (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1991 Festival administration files - Case for Support report (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1991 Festival administration files - Shakespeare in the Schools (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1992 Festival administration files (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1992 Festival administration files - Case for Support report (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1993 Festival administration files, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
    - 1993 Festival administration files - Case for Support report (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - 1993 Festival administration files - Draft planning document, November 1993 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - 1994 Festival administration files, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
    - 1994 Festival administration files - Merchant of Venice (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - 1994 Festival administration files - Taming of the Shrew (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - 1995 Festival administration files, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - 1995 Festival administration files - Shakespeare in the Schools (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Henry IV, Part I, 1983; 2.
    Henry IV, Part I was a part of the 1983 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, June 16 through July 2.
    - Audio recording, May 27, 1983; 1 reel-to-reel (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Audio recording - Reading of the play for the blind, 1 cassette_tape 50 minutes (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Braille action score, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Production materials, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
    - Promptbook, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
    - Slides (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Macbeth, 1984-1988; 3.
    Macbeth was a part of the 1984 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, June 1st through the 23rd.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Director's notes, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Press materials, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Production materials, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21-26)
    - Production notes, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Promptbook, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Slides (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - A Midsummer Night's Dream, 1986; 4.
    A Midsummer Night's Dream was a part of the 1986 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, May 30th through June 22nd. Leading up to it's opening at the end of May, the production was performed at several local high schools.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Production materials, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
    - Slides (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Two Gentlemen of Verona, 1987-1992; 5.
    Two Gentlemen of Verona was a part of the 1987 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, May 29th through June 20th. Leading up to it's opening at the end of May, the production was performed at several local high schools. There are materials related to both the 1987 production and the 1992 revival in each of the two's promptbooks.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Audio recording, 3 cassette_tapes (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Oversized photograph (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Production materials, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
    - Promptbook, 1987-1992 (Box 3, Folder 16-21)
    - Score, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Script, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Slides (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Julius Caesar, 1988; 6.
    Julius Caesar was a part of the 1988 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, July 22nd through August 14th.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Production materials, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
    - Promptbook, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Slides (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Maids and Blades, 1988; 7.
    Maids and Blades was a compilation of scenes from Shakespeare's plays performed by the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival Young Company in the Fall of 1988. The touring production was performed at local Pittsburgh high school and junior high schools. The scenes performed were from Henry V, Henry IV, As You Like It, Twelfth Night, Romeo and Juliet, and The Taming of the Shrew.
    - Production materials, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Taming of the Shrew, 1987-1988; 8.
    The Taming of the Shrew was a part of the 1988 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. Coleman also played the part of Petruchio in the production. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, May 27th through June 19th. The video recording included is of very poor quality.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Production materials, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Promptbook, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Video recording - Rehearsal, 1 cassette_tape VHS, 152 minutes (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum, 1989; 9.
    A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum was a part of the 1989 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival, its 10th anniversary season. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, June 4th through July 15th.
    - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Promptbook, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
  - Richard II, 1990; 10.
    Richard II was a part of the 1990 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, June 22nd through July 14th.
    - Annotated acting editions (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Promptbook, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 16-18)
    - Slides (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Othello, 1990-1991; 11.
    Othello was a part of the 1991 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, May 24th through June 15th.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Production materials, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Promptbook, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Slides (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Two Gentlemen of Verona, 1987-1999; 12.
    Two Gentlemen of Verona was a part of the 1992 season of the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, May 15th through June 6th. There are materials related to both the 1987 production and the 1992 revival in each of the two's promptbooks.
    - Production materials, 1992-1999 (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
    - Promptbook, 1987-1992 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
    - Slides (Box 5, Folder 11)
- University of Pittsburgh Repertory Theatre, 1981-2009; II.
  This series contains promptbooks and production materials from Pitt Repertory Theatre for which W. Stephen Coleman served as a Faculty Director and Professor of Theatre Arts. This series details the repertory production of Hamlet and Rosencrantz and Guildenstern are Dead (1996), which was submitted to the American College Theatre Festival. The materials related to this production include a letter from playwright Tom Stoppard. Coleman directed the gala production of Much Ado About Nothing (2003) for the opening of the renovated Charity Randall Theatre and Coleman's scenic design and production book for Arms and the Man (2004) are included in this series.
  - All the Way Home, 1981-1982; 1.
    Coleman's first production as director at the University of Pittsburgh was the play All the Way Home. It was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, March 4-20, 1982. Production materials include audition forms that were also used for the City Theatre's production of Indians.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, May 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Production materials, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
    - Promptbook, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 16-18)
    - Slides (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - A Phoenix Too Frequent, 1982; 2.
    A Phoenix Too Frequent, directed by Coleman, was performed at the Studio Theatre, November 8-10, 15-17, 1982. The play was presented along with Ludlow Fair and the Public Eye, which were directed by Jane Rothman and Lamont Arnold respectively.
    - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Promptbook, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Slides (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Brecht on Brecht, 1982-1983; 3.
    Brecht on Brecht was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, February 11-26, 1983.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Production materials, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Promptbook, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Cherry Orchard, 4.
    - Production materials (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Promptbook (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Slides (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Orpheus Descending, 1983-1984; 5.
    Orpheus Descending was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, March 8-24, 1984.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Music, 1 reel-to-reel (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Photographs and negatives (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Production materials, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
    - Promptbook, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The Ruling Class, 1984-1985; 6.
    The Ruling Class was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, March 21st through April 6th, 1985.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Photographs, July 1985 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Production materials, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Promptbook, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Slides (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Cloud 9, 1985-1986; 7.
    Cloud 9 was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, October 31st through November 16, 1985. It was revived for two special performances in February of 1986 and was performed at the Annual American College Theatre Festival XVIII in Hyattsville, Maryland.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Photographs (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Production materials, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
    - Promptbook, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 25-26)
  - Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf, 1986-1987; 8.
    Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, February 6-28, 1987.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Audio recording - George's Act II story performed by John Krich, 1 cassette_tape 7 minutes (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Photographs, April 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Production materials, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Promptbook, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Slides (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Cherry Orchard, 1988-1989; 9.
    Scope and Contents
    The Cherry Orchard was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, October 28 - November 12, 1988.
    - Photographs, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Production materials, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Oresteia, 1989-1990; 10.
    Oresteia was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, March 23rd through April 7th, 1990.
    - Audio recording, 1 cassette_tape 35 minutes (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, August 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Production materials, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Slides (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Sound effects demo recording, 1 cassette_tape 50 minutes (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Happy End, 1989-1991; 11.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Production materials, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - The Changeling: A Re/Vision, 1991-1992; 12.
    The Changeling: Re/Vision was performed at the Studio Theatre, February 14-29, 1992. Thomas Middleton and William Rowley's 17th century play The Changeling was adapted by Theatre Arts faculty member Dennis Kennedy. The play evolved out of a series of eight workshops during the Fall semester of 1991. The majority of these workshops were recorded and are contained within this section. Also included in this section are video recordings that were used in the production itself.
    - Production materials, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Promptbook, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
    - Video recording - Roll A-C, 3 cassette_tapes VHS (Box 8)
    - Video recording - Workshops, 1991; 9 cassette_tapes VHS (Box 8)
  - A Month in the Country, 1992-1993; 13.
    A Month in the Country was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, February 12-28, 1993.
    - Promptbook, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 20-21)
  - The Rehearsal, 1993; 14.
    The Rehearsal was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, October 8-23, 1993.
    - Production materials, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Promptbook, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Chemin de Fer, 1994-1995; 15.
    Chemin de Fer was performed at the Stephen Foster Memorial Theatre, February 10-25, 1995.
    - Annotated acting edition (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Promptbook, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Les Liaisons Dangereuses, 1995; 16.